<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model
  href="https://vault.tei-c.org/P5/current/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng"
  schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"
  type="application/xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title> History of the Rise and Fall of the Roman Empire </title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher> Tufts Intro to DH Spring 2026 </publisher>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>
          https://archive.org/details/historyofdeclinex01gibb/page/n25/mode/2up
        </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>

  <text>
    <body>
      <milestone unit="rule" rend="double"/>
      <div type="Title" rend="centered">
        <head rend="smallcaps"> THE </head>
        <head> HISTORY </head>
        <head rend="smallcaps"> OF THE </head>
        <head> DECLINE AND FALL </head>
        <head rend="smallcaps"> OF THE </head>
        <head> ROMAN EMPIRE </head>
      </div>
      <milestone unit="rule"/>
      <div type="Title" subtype="Chapter">
        <l rend="center">CHAP. I.</l>
        <l rend="center"> The Extent and Military Force of the Empire in the Age <lb /> of the
          Antonines. </l>

        <note place="margin" n="1"> CHAP. <lb /> I. <lb /> Introduction. <metamark function="brace"
            rend="underbrace" />
        </note>
        <p>
          <hi rend="dropcap">I</hi>N the ſecond century of the Chriſtian Æra, the empire of Rome
          comprehended the faireſt part of the earth, and the moſt ci- <lb break="no" />
          vilized portion of mankind. The frontiers of that extenſive <lb/>
          monarchy were guarded by ancient renown and diſciplined valour. <lb/>
          The gentle, but powerful influence of laws and manners had gra- <lb break="no" />
          dually cemented the union of the provinces. Their peaceful in- <lb break="no" />
          habitants enjoyed and abuſed the advantages of wealth and luxury. <lb/>
          The image of a free conſtitution was preſerved with decent reverence: <lb/>
          The Roman ſenate appeared to poſſeſs the ſovereign authority, and <lb/>
          devolved on the emperors all the executive powers of government.
          During a happy period of more than fourſcore years, the public <lb/>
        </p>
        <note place="margin">A. D. 98-- <lb/> 180.</note>
         <p>
          adminiſtration was conducted by the virtue and abilities of Nerva, <lb/>
          Trajan, Hadrian, and the two Antonines. It is the deſign of this <lb/>
          and of the two ſucceeding chapters, to deſcribe the proſperous con- <lb break="no"/>
          dition of their empire; and afterwards, from the death of Marcus <lb/>
        </p>
        <fw type="runningFooter" place="bottom">
          <seg rend="smallcaps">VOL. I.</seg>
          <seg rend="sig">B</seg>
          <seg rend="catch">Antoninus,</seg>
        </fw>


      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>